<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A mystery which the angels desired to look into. 1 Pet. 1. 11. 12.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89440</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3192</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E386_15*</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201484</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861989</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861989</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160225</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89440)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160225)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 61:E386[15*])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A mystery which the angels desired to look into. 1 Pet. 1. 11. 12.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>"A religious dissertation"--Thomason Catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 12 1647".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 1st, I, 11-12 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:160225:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Myſtery which the Angels deſired to look into. <hi>1 PET. 1.11.12.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He end why the Eternall Father did ſend the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and now ſends his Miniſters, is, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſets it down, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.9. <hi>To make all men ſee what is the fellowſhip of the myſtery which from the beginning of the world hath been hid in God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>To the intent that now unto the principalities and powers in heavenly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> (<hi>i.</hi> to the Angels even of higheſt degree) <hi>might be known by the Church the manifold wiſdom of God.</hi> But what was this manifold wiſdom? When God had ſuffered <hi>Adam</hi> to fall,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.24.</note> that he might ſee his own pride and folly, Divine Juſtice drave him out of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and placed at the Eaſt end of the garden of Eden Cherubims and a flaming ſword, which turned every way to keep the way of the tree of life; that ſo fleſh nor blood neither might nor could enter. But Divine Wiſdom hath found out a way whereby a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entrance is made; And yet the Decree of Gods juſtice ſtands un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altered, His wiſdom, goodneſſe, and mercy manifeſted, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably fallen men reſtored: Which when the Angels ſaw they ſang for joy, ſaying, <note place="margin">Luk. 2.24.</note>
               <hi>Glory be to God in the higheſt, on earth peace, good will towards men.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The way and myſtery was thus.</head>
               <p>That as in pleaſing the fleſh, the eyes, and the minde, Paradiſe was loſt (for ſo it was) <hi>Eve</hi> ſeeing that the forbidden fruit was good for food, pleaſant to the eyes, and a tree to be deſired to make one wiſe, took and did eat, and gave <hi>Adam,</hi> and he did eat alſo. And ſo both they and their whole poſterity, according to a Decree of Almighty God, were caſt out of Paradiſe, left without God in a miſerable world, ſubject to labour and ſorrow till death ſeized on them; and then alſo were without hope of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection or ſecond life. But Divine Wiſdom out of a bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Fountain of love, ordained that as in pleaſing the fleſh, the eye, and the minde, Paradiſe was loſt, and conſequently all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:160225:2"/>wo, and death it ſelf purchaſed; So in diſpleaſing theſe three, <hi>viz.</hi> the fleſh, the eye, and the minde, and paſſing by thoſe fiery Cherubims, ſuffering death for a good conſcience, or at leaſt reſigning our ſelf thereunto, Paradiſe with a ſecond life might be regained. But this when frail man, becauſe he was but fleſh,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.3.</note> could not do; The Son of God was content to take our fleſh upon him, and in this fleſh make his own life exemplary for all men, ſhewing them how they muſt follow him in way of regra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; that as they had loſt Paradiſe by pleaſing the fleſh, the eyes, and the minde, by which death had paſſed upon all; So they ſhould regain it by renouncing them, and following him in a voluntary abaſed humiliation, to the loſſe of all worldly things.<note place="margin">Rev. 2.7.</note> They that thus overcome, as he overcame, ſhall go in, and eat of the tree of life which is in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God, and live for ever, be with him, live and reign with him for ever and ever. This is that everlaſting Goſpel or glad tydings preached unto men.</p>
               <p>But becauſe for this work the Son of God was to leave his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers boſome, and the glory which he had with him in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt heavens, and ſo deſcending upon the earth, muſt take mans frail nature upon him, and in that nature muſt be abaſed and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, ſuffering hunger, cold, nakedneſſe, induring ignominy, ſhame,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.5.10.</note> reproach, and at laſt dye the moſt curſed and painfull death, even the death of the Croſſe; for this his great humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he obtain'd of his Father, by way of reward, an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary exaltation. It was decreed he ſhould not onely be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved up into glory,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.6.</note> but in the higheſt heavens ſit on the right hand of God Almighty, where all the Angels of God ſhould worſhip him: And he ſhould be Prince of this his Church, which he had purchaſed with his own blood, and ſhould have all power put into his hands, both of things in heaven, and things in earth, and things under the earth, and ſhould be judge of men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. Yea moreover it was granted, that for his ſake, and for his great humiliation, all his followers ſhould have their ſins for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given them; but the ſpots and ſtains thereof muſt be waſhed away by the water of affliction. For there are foure things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in ſin, the act, the guilt, the ſtain, the ſcandall: The act is ſoon over, the guilt remains till removed by repentance, and then though in the Court of heaven atonement be made by Chriſts blood,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.</note> as in the caſe of <hi>Davids</hi> murther and adultery; yet
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:160225:2"/>the ſtain and ſcandall continues, and according to the nature of the offence is waſhed away by the water of affliction through the Word (a figure of which was the Ark ſaving of eight perſons in the old world by water;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.9. &amp; 26. 1 Pet. 3.20, 21</note> and the like figure whereunto doth Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme now ſave, obſerved by St. <hi>Peter</hi> to be both figures.) Now this is performed either by a mortified life, or the afflicting hand of God, or both: As appears by that example of <hi>David,</hi> alſo of <hi>Miriam</hi> her murmuring againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> and many that ſinned in the wilderneſſe. And therefore it is, ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that the Lord doth judge and chaſtiſe men, that they ſhould not be condemned with the world.</p>
               <p>And that this ſhould be the condition of Gods children,<note place="margin">Gen. 7. Exod. 3.2; Exod. 14 29. 1 Sam. 14. Dan. 3. Ioh 3.6. Matth. 14.24.</note> was long ago plainly prefigured by <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark floating upon the roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing floods; by <hi>Moſes</hi> burning buſh, by the Iſraelites paſſing tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Red ſea; by the taking of the Ark of God, by the uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed Philiſtines, by the three Children walking up &amp; down in the fiery fornace. Again, under the Goſpel, by <hi>John</hi> baptizing the people in Jordan; By St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſhip toſſed to and fro with a winde which was contrary;<note place="margin">Rev. 12. Exod 2.3.</note> and by the Dragons perſecuting the woman in the wilderneſſe. It was ſo in the time of the Law. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> no ſooner born, but layed in the flags by the river ſide.<note place="margin">Gen. 37.26. Iſa 53.4. Exod. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſold into Aegypt. <hi>David,</hi> a man of ſorrows. The Children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael no ſooner from under <hi>Pharaohs</hi> hard bondage, but they are in the wilderneſſe where they muſt wander fourty yeers. It were too long to run through all their miſeries, beſides their two cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivities. Yet all this they hoped would end when Meſſiah came, then they expected Halcyon dayes. But it's no better yet, for ſince the dayes of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 11.12.</note> the kingdom of heaven ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth violence, and onely the violent take it by force. His Diſciples indeed thought that he would have reſtored the Kingdom to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,<note place="margin">Act. 1.6.</note> but he tels them they were deceived in looking for a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom here. They that would be his followers,<note place="margin">Luk. 10 13.</note> muſt carry a Croſſe upon their ſhoulders, and not a Crown upon their heads, unleſſe of thorns. And when he ſent out his twelve Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Matth. 10.10.</note> and that a large journey, to preach the Goſpel over all the world; He doth not provide them with as much as neceſſaries, but plainly bids them, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.4. <hi>carry neither purſe, nor ſcrip, nor ſhoes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 14.26.</note> provide nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gold, nor ſilver, nor braſſe. A hard Chapter! yet to teach it them the better, he would give them an example. Nay (with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence be it ſpoken) he muſt do it. It behoved him, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2. it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoved
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:160225:3"/>him to ſuffer, and ſo to enter into glory; And it behoveth us as much.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.12.</note> He calleth us indeed to a kingdom, but it is upon condition of ſuffering. <hi>If we ſuffer, we ſhall alſo reign with him.</hi> There is no promiſe otherwiſe. A thing ſo well known to the Primitive Chriſtians,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.3.</note> that St. <hi>Paul</hi> tels the Theſſalonians, yea your ſelves know we are appointed to ſuffer; God hath predeſtinated us thereunto.<note place="margin">Rom 8.30.</note> 
                  <hi>For whom be foreknew, he alſo did predeſtinate to be conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the image of his Son. Moreover, whom he did predeſtinate, them he alſo called:</hi> he called to ſufferings, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.3.9. <hi>For even here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto were ye called: becauſe Christ alſo ſuffered for us, leaving us an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 10.30. Mat. 16 24, 25 Luk. 29.23, 24. Luk. 14.16.27 Ioh. 12.15.</note> 
                  <hi>that we ſhould follow his ſteps. For whoſoever will ſave his life, ſhall loſe it: and whoſoever will loſe his life for my ſake,</hi> ſaith our Lord, <hi>ſhall find it.</hi> And therefore <hi>if any man will be my diſciple, and come after me, let him deny himſelf, and take up his croſſe daily, and follow me.</hi> This is our Lords doctrine left to his Church; and as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, his members muſt <hi>fill up that which is behinde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1.24. Luk 12.4.</note> 
                  <hi>of the afflictions of his fleſh for his bodies ſake which is his Church:</hi> and thoſe that ſo do are his friends.<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.14.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſay unto you my friends, fear not them which kill the body.</hi> And again, <hi>Ye are my friends, if ye do whatſoever I command you.</hi> Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth I call you not ſervants, but friends: ſuch an one was <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 2.23.</note> who in temptations and extremities truſted in God, which was counted or imputed unto him for righteouſneſſe, and he was called the friend of God.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.3.</note> So are all thoſe that follow <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſteps, friends of God, if ye do what Chriſt commands, leave this world with the pleaſures thereof.</p>
               <p>If any deſired to be helped to tranquillity, as <hi>Zebedees</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren did,<note place="margin">Mar. 10.39.</note> he tels them that they muſt drink of his Cup, that bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Cup of his paſſion: <hi>Matth</hi> 26.39. and be baptized with his Baptiſme.<note place="margin">Mar. 9.49.</note> Every one muſt be ſalted with fire, which doubtleſſe is all one with to be baptized with fire. <hi>Matth</hi> 3.11. And this may be the meaning of that place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15. <hi>He ſhall be ſaved; yet ſo as by fire:</hi> which by ſome is applyed to Purgatory. But affliction is the true Purgatory. This is that Refiners fire, and fullers ſope purifying the ſons of <hi>Levi, Mal.</hi> 3.2, 3. which is ſo terrible, that at the firſt ſight the Prophet asketh the queſtion, <hi>Who can abide the day of his coming? or who ſhall ſtand when he appeareth?</hi> Who will follow him, and ſuffer the Croſſe, the loſſe of all to come to a kingdom? This is that ſpirit of judgement, and ſpirit of burning that waſheth away the filth of the daughter of Sion, and purgeth away the blood of Jeruſalem from the midſt of her. This is that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:160225:3"/>cleanſing fanne by which the floore ſhall be throughly purged.<note place="margin">Iſa 4.4 Matt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.12. Rev. 7 14.</note> Therefore it is, that thoſe that are arrayed in white robes are ſaid to come out of great tribulation, waſhing their robes in the blood of the Lambe.<note place="margin">Matt. 18 19.</note> And whatſoever good thing is condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible or helpfull to any, that they may the better follow Chriſt in this his humiliation, and thereby be regenerated, and made one with him and his Father, he promiſeth to grant them, yea in this way,<note place="margin">Matt 21.22. Iam. 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Hab 2.4.</note> and for this end onely (not for mens luſts) but to ſit them for heaven, ask what ye will, ſaith our Lord, and ye ſhall have it. In this condition or ſtate of affliction, the Juſt lives by his faith, relying on God, and waiting the performance of his promiſe. As it is written, <note place="margin">Iſa. 28 16.</note>he that beleeves makes not haſte, goes not out of Gods preſence from this or that trouble; but with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Job</hi> waits the Lords leiſure, going from trouble to trouble, from faith to faith, from ſtrength to ſtrength, as Iſrael did,<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.7.</note> from one ſtation to another, through the wilderneſſe to Canaan, a type of our journey through the deſert of this world,<note place="margin">Iſa. 40.30.</note> towards our heavenly Canaan. Though the youth faint, and are weary, and the young men utterly fail, yet they that wait on the Lord ſhall renew their ſtrength. <hi>They ſhall run, and not be weary, they ſhall walke, and not faint.</hi> For in this path doth Gods power keep the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an through faith (who in all extremities relyes upon him) to that Salvation ready to be revealed in the laſt time,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.5.</note> which is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thing he waiteth for.<note place="margin">Iſa. 43.2.</note> In the interim <hi>though he paſſe through the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters God will be with him; and thorow the rivers, they ſhall not overflow him. When he walketh through the fire he ſhall not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 54.17.</note> 
                  <hi>No weapon that is formed againſt him ſhall proſper;</hi> for ſtrong is the Lord that keepeth him; Not the outward man from deſtruction, that's decreed,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.16. Zach. 2.8.</note> and in due time muſt be deſtroyed; but the inward man, and welfare of it. He that touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that, toucheth the apple of Gods eye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But what, may ſome ſay, needs all this? may we not live merrily, avoid trouble as much as we can, and yet go to heaven in the end?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aaſ.</hi> I anſwer. We read of ſome indeed that become old, and are mighty in power, <hi>Job</hi> 21. <hi>Their houſes are ſafe from fear, neither is the rod of God upon them. Their Bull genders, and Cow calveth: they ſend out their little ones like flocks, and their children dance, are brought up to Muſick, for they take the timbrel and the harp, and raj yee at the ſound of the Organ; But they are wicked,</hi> ver. 7. <hi>and in a moment go down
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:160225:4"/>to hell.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 49.</note> ver. 13. <hi>O my ſoul, come not thou into their ſecrets, into their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, mine honour, be not thou united.</hi> For theſe are men that have their portions in this life,<note place="margin">Eccle. 3.</note> whoſe bellies God fils with the hid treaſures thereof. But it's better to go into the houſe of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then into the houſe of feaſting. Sorrow is better then laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for by the ſadneſſe of the countenance the heart is made bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and merrier.<note place="margin">Eccl. 3.4.</note> And the wiſe man ſaith, there is <hi>a time to weep, and a time to laugh:</hi> but the laughing time comes laſt. So ſaid <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> to <hi>Dives,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk 16.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Remember that thou in thy life time receivedſt thy good things, and likewiſe Lazarus evill things; but now he is comforted, and thou art tormented.</hi> As both of them, ſo all of us have allotted from the hand of Gods providence bad and good things, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and comforts:<note place="margin">Pſal. 126.5, 6.</note> they that ſowe in joy, ſhall reap in tears; and they that ſowe in tears, ſhall reap in joy. <hi>He that goeth forth weeping, bearing precious ſeed, ſhall doubtleſſe come again with joy, and bring his ſheaves with him.</hi> Thoſe that weep may be comforted, and thoſe that are perſecuted may leap for joy; for Chriſt hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced them thrice bleſſed,<note place="margin">Luk 6.24, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 6. whileſt thoſe that are full, and laugh, and of whom the world ſpeaketh well, have as many woes. <hi>Wo unto you that are rich, for ye have received your conſolation. Wo unto you that are full, for ye ſhall hunger. Wo unto you that laugh now: for ye ſhall mourn and weep.</hi> Luk. 6.24, 25.</p>
               <p>Hence it comes to paſſe, that the true Chriſtian, whoſe eyes God hath opened to ſee theſe things, laugheth at calamities, and mocketh when fear cometh,<note place="margin">Pro. 1.26.</note> and deſolation like a whirlwinde. For he (namely, the inward man) is in that <hi>Dothan</hi> about which are horſes of fire,<note place="margin">2 King 6.13.17,</note> and chariots of fire compaſſing. Although there ſhould be no meat in fields, flocks in folds, nor herds in ſtalls, yet I will rejoyce in the Lord,<note place="margin">Hab 3.17, 18.</note> ſaith <hi>Habbakkuk,</hi> I will joy in the God of my ſalvation. For the Lord God is my ſtrength, he will make my feet like hindes feet, and I ſhall walk upon my high places. And ſuch as ſuffer for righteouſneſſe are counted worthy of the kingdom,<note place="margin">Rev. 3.4.</note> which the Father hath prepared for thoſe that love him. Therefore the Apoſtles rejoyced over the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> for their faith in perſecutions, and tribulations that they endured, <hi>which is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a manifest token of the righteous judgement of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Theſ 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>that ye may be counted worthy of the kingdom for which ye alſo ſuffer; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it's a righteous thing to recompence tribulation on them that trouble us, and to them who are troubled rest with us.</hi> As for the Apoſtle himſelf, who knew the truth of theſe things, his whole ſtudy was the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:160225:4"/>of the Croſſe; he deſired to know nothing elſe but Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified: <hi>God forbid,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note> 
                  <hi>that I ſhould glory in any thing, ſave in the croſſe of our Lord Jeſus Christ, by whom the world is crucified to me, and I unto the world.</hi> And in this he glorieth, that he twice in one Chap. makes an apologie, as fearing leſt men ſhould think him a fool for boaſting ſo much: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1.16. And then begins: <hi>I will glory of the things which concern mine infirmities.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.8.9, 10.10 30.</note> 
                  <hi>In Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>In ſtripes above meaſure, in priſons frequent, in deaths oft. Of the Jews five times received I fourty ſtripes ſave one, thrice was I beaten with rods, once was I ſtoned, thrice I ſuffered ſhipwrack. A night and a day I have been in the deep: in journeying often, in perils of waters, in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of robbers, in perils by mine own Countreymen, and in perils by the heathen: in perils in the City, in the wilderneſſe, in the ſea, in perils a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst falſe brethren, in wearineſſe, in painfulneſſe, in hunger and thirſt, in faſting oft, in cold and nakedneſſe.</hi> And <hi>beſides thoſe things that are without, that which cometh on me daily, the care of all the Churches. And if I muſt needs glory, I will glory in the things which concern mine infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</hi> For when I am weak, then am I ſtrong; the more I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, the more Chriſt inables me. And ſaith the Apoſtle in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, by this <hi>we bear in our bodies the dying of our Lord Jeſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor 4 11.</note> 
                  <hi>that the life alſo of Jeſus might be made manifeſt in our mortall bodies.</hi> Thus <hi>the Lord tryeth the righteous, but the wicked,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 11.5. Pro. 3.12. Eccl. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and him that loveth violence, his ſoul bateth. For whom he loveth, he chaſtneth, even as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſon, in whom he delighteth.</hi> For gold is tryed in the fire; and acceptable men in the furnace of Affliction. What man is ſo foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh as rather to deſire gold mingled with droſſe, than to have it paſſe the fire? Thus God ſerved Jeruſalem, <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.9. He tels the people he will bring them through the fire, and refine them as ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is refined, and will try them as gold is tryed. Then ſhall they call on his Name, and he will hear them: he will ſay, It is my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and they ſhall ſay, The Lord is my God.<note place="margin">Indich 8.22, 23, 24. Iam. 2.23.</note> Thus was our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abraham</hi> tryed, and being proved by many tribulations, was made the friend of God: Thus <hi>Iſaac,</hi> thus <hi>Jacob,</hi> thus <hi>Moſes,</hi> and all who pleaſed God, by many tribulations became faithfull.<note place="margin">Wiſd 3.5.</note> That having a little been chaſtiſed, they might be greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded.</p>
               <p>Thus is made known unto us the myſtery of Godlineſſe, which the Apoſtle ſaith is great;<note place="margin">1 Tim 3 1.</note> and without controverſie it is the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery which in other Ages was not made known unto the ſons of men, as it is now revealed to Gods holy Apoſtles and Prophets
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:160225:5"/>by his Spirit, that they might preach the unſearchable riches of Chriſt obtained by the Croſſe; of which the ancient Prophets en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and ſearched diligently; who propheſied of the grace that ſhould come, ſearching what, and what manner of time the Spirit of Chriſt which was in them did ſignifie, which teſtified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand of the ſufferings of Chriſt, and the glory that ſhould follow: which things the Angels defire to look into. A figure of which were the two Cherubims with their wings lifted up, but their face looking one towards another, and toward the Mercy ſeat; which myſtery being revealed to the holy Apoſtles by the holy Ghoſt ſent down from heaven, and by them manifeſted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Angels, may miniſter ſome ground why the Angels admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of adoration in the Old Teſtament, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.31, 32. <hi>Joſ.</hi> 5.14. and refuſed it in the New. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10. and 22.10.</p>
               <p>Thus doth it manifeſtly appear, that there is no other way to be ſaved but by the Croſſe of Chriſt, to conform our ſelves to his ſufferings, to follow him in his abaſed humiliation; that ſo we may be like him in his exaltation. For as he was, ſo are we in this preſent evill world.<note place="margin">1 Ioh 4.7.</note> This he hath taught us both by his doctrine and life. And ſurely had there been any other way, he would have ſhewed it us. And let us conſider though the forbidden fruit might be reall to <hi>Adam,</hi> yet unto us as it hath an influence, upon theſe three, <hi>viz.</hi> the fleſh, the eyes, the minde, it is a figure anſwering thereunto. St. <hi>James</hi> eſteemes the wiſdom &amp; ſtrength layed out upon theſe, to be earthly, ſenſuall, divelliſh. Of the ſame ſpeaks St. <hi>John,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioh 2.15, 16</note> ſaying, <hi>Love not the world, nor the things that are in the world. For all that is in the world, the luſts of the fleſh, the luſts of the eyes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>and the pride of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world.</hi> And our Lord dyed to <hi>deliver us from this preſent evill world:</hi> from which S. <hi>James</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.27.</note> he that is religious keeps himſelf unſpotted.</p>
               <p>Every offence that in this world is committed, is either for a beaſtly pleaſure, a trifling commodity, or for ſome vain eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with man. And as in a glaſſe face anſwers face, ſo do theſe three kinds of tranſgreſſions to thoſe three qualities of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit: <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. And therefore it is that the Chriſtian in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme promiſes to renounce theſe three, the world, the fleſh, and the devill, and to follow our Lord under the Croſſe; the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of which through Chriſt is that which ſaveth, called by the Apoſtle not the waſhing away the ſilth of the fleſh, but the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of a good conſcience. And this is that ſpirituall and fiery
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:160225:5"/>Baptiſme of Chriſt, namely, a Baptiſme into his death; unto which whoſoever ſubſcribes, ſtands ingaged to a crucifixion, and daily death for a good conſcience;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> and is in jeopardy to dye eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry houre. As it is written, if the dead riſe not, why are we bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed for the dead? and why ſtand we in jeopardy every houre? I proteſt, ſaith the Apoſtle, by our rejoycing which I have in Chriſt Jeſus I dye daily: therefore it is that the Lord Chriſt to the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized is a Captain, a Leader; and every ſuch that hath reſigned up himſelf to be his Souldier, and to follow the Lambe where-ever he goeth, this his skilfull Captain will lead through crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed paths, and bring fear and dread upon him,<note place="margin">Ecclu 4.11 18.</note> and torment him by diſcipline; but after will comfort him, and ſhew him ſecrets. Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>After ye have ſuffered a while,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5 10.</note> 
                  <hi>he ſhall ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh, ſtrengthen, ſettle you.</hi> This is the Lords way to ſave the ſons of men. And as <hi>Eiihu</hi> ſaid, theſe things God worketh thrice, yea of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with man, to bring back his ſoul from the pit, to be enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the light of the living.<note place="margin">Iob 23.</note> That man whom God intends to dignifie, he viſits every morning, and tryes him every moment,<note place="margin">Iob 7. Hebr. 12.</note> and chaſtiſeth him for his profit, that ſo he may be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of Gods holineſſe; indeed be regenerated, made one with the Father, and the Son, as our Lord ſaid, Verily, ye which have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed me in the regeneration, when the Son of man ſhall ſit upon the throne of his glory, ye ſhall ſit upon twelve thrones judging the Tribes of Iſrael. Every one that hath forſaken houſes, or bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands, for my Names ſake, ſhall receive an hundred fold, and ſhall inberit everlaſting life. This in our Lords opinion is the very means of mans regeneration, namely,<note place="margin">Iſa 51.2, 3. Pſ 1 44. Iob 34.7. Iſa. 50.6.</note> a patient following him through all afflictions, to be as a lambe dumbe before the ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers; to lay the body as the ground, and as the ſtreet to them that paſſe over; patiently bearing reproaches, and drinking down ſcorning like water; to give the back to the ſmiters, the face to the ſpitters, and the checks to them that pluck off the hair. But this doctrine to fleſh and blood ſeems ſtrange, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, Lord, who hath beleeved our report?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1 23.</note> To the Jews it is a ſtumbling block, to the Greeks fooliſhneſſe:<note place="margin">Hab. 2.10. and 5.9.</note> but to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian beleever it is the power of God to ſalvation. For by means of the Croſſe, the Chriſtian is made like his Maſter, fitted for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and perfected as he was perfected;<note place="margin">Hab 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0 59.</note> and he that endureth moſt for him in this life, that comes neereſt to him in ſuilerings, ſhall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:160225:6"/>come neereſt to him in glory in the next. Therfore let us not think afflictions (when God ſendeth them) ſo ſtrange a thing,<note place="margin">Job 7.17, 11.</note> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with holy <hi>Job</hi> in ſecret (admiring that God ſhould take ſuch care for to make us partakers of his holineſſe) ſay,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord what is man that thou ſhouldſt dignifie him? that thou ſhouldſt ſet thy heart upon him? that thou ſhou'dſt viſit him every morning, and try him every moment?</hi> But Lord, what may be thought of thoſe men that take up the ſword againſt the Creſſe? Thoſe that have cauſed ſo great effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſtian blood for liberty,<note place="margin">Ieſuites and heady Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</note> yea liberty to the fleſh, which muſt be crucified, that ſo they mayſerve God as themſelves pleaſe; and that without any trouble in this world. How are theſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and alſo Enemies of the Croſſe of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>The holy Apoſtle wept to think that there ſhould be any ſuch among Chriſtians;<note place="margin">Phil. 3.19.</note> telling the Philippians that ſuch made their belly their God, their glory their ſhame, earthly minded men, their end was deſtruction. Alas, alas! what ſhall become of thoſe among Chriſtians, that for this end, becauſe they may not have liberty, ſpeak evill of Dignities, and deſpiſe Dominions, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the foot-ſteps of <hi>Cain, Corab, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and will not be warned by their judgements? Which examples as ſtanding Pillars of Salt remain to all generations. Wo is them, wo is them, for them in eſpeciall, ſaith St. <hi>Jude,</hi> is reſerved blackneſſe, and darkneſſe for ever. <hi>Jude</hi> 8.13.</p>
               <p>Did the bleſſed Trinity in their wiſdom finde out this onely means for the reſtauration of loſt mankinde? Did the holy Apoſtles rejoyce in it? the Angels admire it? the univerſall Church imbrace it? and do we fight to make it void? The very thoughts thereof cauſe my knees to tremble, my lips to quiver, and rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to enter into my bones. For God with vengeance will come with thouſands of his Saints, as <hi>Enoch</hi> propheſied, to execute judgement on all belly gods that are ungodly among them, of all their ungodly deeds, and of all their hard ſpeeches which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ſinners have ſpoken againſt him.</p>
               <p>Theſe,<note place="margin">Iude 19.</note> ſaith that Apoſtle, are thoſe that ſeparate themſelves, ſenſuall,<note place="margin">Ier 7.29.</note> not having the Spirit. O Lord what have we done? that thou ſhouldſt ſuffer us to ſtray, and in knowing times to be ſo ſtrangely deluded.</p>
               <p>By what degrees of ſins have we aſcended to ſuch unmatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able wickedneſſe. O! the Chriſtian Religion how it is diſgraced! Cut off thy hair,<note place="margin">Ier. 7.29.</note> O Chriſtian, and caſt it from thee, and take up
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:160225:6"/>a lamentation in all thy publick places, and ſay:</p>
               <p>O Lord, if it be poſſible open our eyes,<note place="margin">Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 19.18. Act 1.23.</note> and remove this bitter Gall, forgive this great iniquitie. When Iſrael had ſinned in making the golden Calf, thou ſhewedſt mercy upon thouſands. To <hi>Manaſſes</hi> which cauſed Jeruſalem to ſwim with innocent blood, and had no works of righteouſneſſe.<note place="margin">Exod. 23. 2 King 11.16.</note> Thou declaredſt thy great mercy in pardoning him. Thou reſtoredſt Iſrael from cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, which had lived like beaſts.<note place="margin">2 Eſds 8.29, 30</note> The Thief upon the Croſſe had nothing but ſins to preſent thee with, yet thou pardoneſt him, for thou art a God of mercy, art call'd mercifull,<note place="margin">Ier. 3.12. Exod. 34.</note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteſt in mercy, and haſt treaſures of goodneſſe layed up for them that have none for themſelves. O Lord hear, and conſider. Look not upon the ſins of thy people, but look on thy Sanctuary and worſhip which lyeth waſte. Defer not to help for thy Names ſake, for thy honour ſake. In pitie for thy Chriſts ſake look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our miſeries, for there is no healing nor help left, and we grow worſe and worſe. Our ſins increaſing are grown up unto the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens. We have committed this great evill, and that Jeſuitically by blood; we think to build our neſts on high above the ſtars,<note place="margin">Hab. 2.9.</note> that ſo in this world we may eſcape the Croſſe of our Lord, and be free from the power of evill. But, O Lord, in ſo doing we have refuſed our own health, the waters of <hi>Shiloh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 56.</note> and put from our ſelves that holy Cup of Salvation, of which our Lord himſelf drank, and himſelf with his own blood tempered and ſeaſoned for ſuch as will be his Diſciples. O Lord in judgement remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber mercy,<note place="margin">Ier. 6.16.</note> and bring us once again to that ancient old good way, that walking therein we may find reſt to our ſouls. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him.</p> 
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. 25.14.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And if any man will do his will, he ſhall know of the doctrine, whether it be of God.</p> 
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Joh. 7.17.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THat you might the better think of that which you and I lately ſpake of touching the ſufferings of Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Poſtſcript.</note> I have committed the ſame to writing; and have here according to my promiſe ſent it you. Think upon it, for it's no vain thing,<note place="margin">Deut. 32.47.</note> but it's that whereby our lives ſhall be prolonged in the Land beyond
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:160225:7"/>Jordan, whitherunto we are going. The neceſſity of the ſerious thinking on this doctrine appears, in that our Lord took ſuch pains with his diſciples to inculcate, radicate, and ſettle it in their hearts. For having ſpoke of their ſufferings, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. <hi>Settle it in your hearts,</hi> ſaith he, ver. 12, 13, 14. In another place, ſaith he, <hi>Let theſe ſayings ſink down into your hearts.</hi> Luk. 10. And again, Theſe things have I ſpoken unto you that you ſhould not be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended; and that when the time cometh, you may remember I told you of them: <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.20. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.14. By all which and many other places, this appeareth a matter of great concernment, and of ſome difficulty to be beleeved. And of this doctrine, or this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,<note place="margin">Iſa, 53.</note> we with the Prophet may well ſay, Lord who hath belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? unto ſuch is the power of God manifeſted, and they <hi>ſhall grow up before him as a tender plant, and as a root out of dry ground.</hi> And without doubt the higheſt favour that the Almighty beſtowed upon the ſons of men, is ability to ſuffer for his Name. It is that great feaſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. to which all are invited. The riches that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company it exceed all the treaſures of Nations; and the people that endure are ſuch as God eſteemeth the world not worthy of. And therefore the holieſt of men, even the Apoſtles, rejoyced that they were counted worthy to ſuffer.</p>
               <p>I have now done. The Lord ſettle theſe ſayings in our hearts, and grant us to be thoſe ſpirituall worſhippers, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.23, 24 not to worſhip the Father with bodily ſacrifice, but in ſpirit and truth: inſtead of Burnt-offerings, to offer up our bodies and ſouls a living ſacrifice, and ſo to account of our ſelves but as ſheep ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to the ſlaughter; and to prepare for bonds and afflictions, which,<note place="margin">Act. 20.23</note> as the holy Ghoſt witneſſeth, abide us in every place: for that through much tribulation and violence, the kingdom of heaven muſt be entred.<note place="margin">Act. 14.22.</note> And that as the grace of flowers fade, ſo may our carnality and worldly pomp, glory and honour decay, decreaſe;<note place="margin">Iam. 1 11. Phil 3.3, 8.</note> yea that we may attain to the high price ſet before us, let's account thoſe things dung; and that we may ſo do, let us watch,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> faſt, pray, give alms, as good Souldiers endure all hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that ſo being faithfull in ſmall things, we may be truſted with great. Which is the earneſt prayer of your faithfull Friend.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi> 
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joh. Downame.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
